<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tamas Nagy</title>
    <description>Bioinformatics graduate student at UCSF. Interested in systems biology, image analysis, math, mountains, photography, and more
</description>
    <link>http://www.tamasnagy.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.tamasnagy.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2015 15:57:48 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2015 15:57:48 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Predicting Drug Candidate Promiscuity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, I gave a presentation to my chemistry seminar class on predicting the promiscuity of small-molecule drug candidates by comparing their structure to the sets of ligands that bind specific proteins. If a drug candidate strongly matches a set of ligands for a certain protein then there is a high probability that it will show off-target effects with that protein. Thus, if a candidate is compared against enough protein-ligand sets then it is likely that we can predict the side-effects of a drug before it enters clinical trials. Using this technique, Keiser et al. were able to identify potential reasons for side effects seen in commonly available drugs &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;keiser_predicting_2009&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/span&gt;. For example, they noticed that Rescriptor, an HIV reverse transcriptase inhibitor, matched the ligand sets of histamine receptors, which could explain the skin rashes observed in patients who were on the drug. They used a variant of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaccard_index&quot;&gt;Jaccard index&lt;/a&gt; known as the Tanimoto coefficient to calculate the similarity between pairs of compounds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[ T_c = \frac{\left| \chi_A \cap \chi_B \right|}{\left| \chi_A \cup \chi_B \right|}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\chi_A\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\chi_B\)&lt;/span&gt; are sets of features that describe compound &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt; and compound &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(B\)&lt;/span&gt;, respectively. My understanding is that they compared the set of ligands for the known target of a drug compound to the all other protein-ligands sets. For each of these set comparisons they computed pairwise &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(T_c\)&lt;/span&gt; values for each ligand in the first set with each ligand in the second set. They then summed all the number of ligand pairs with &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(T_c &amp;gt; 0.57\)&lt;/span&gt; yielding what they termed a &lt;em&gt;raw score&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;hert_quantifying_2008&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/span&gt;. Now, this raw score is biased by the size of the sets and it does not account for randomness. The authors account for this by transforming the raw scores to Z-scores:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[ z = \frac{rs(S_1, S_2 - \mu(n(S_1, S_2)}{\sigma(n(S_1, S_2))}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(rs(S_1,S_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the raw score of set &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(S_1\)&lt;/span&gt; versus. set &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(S_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(n(S_1,S_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the product of the sizes of the two sets, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mu\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\sigma\)&lt;/span&gt; are the expected raw score mean and expected raw score std. dev. Now, they noticed that the background distribution of raw scores for their compound comparisons matched an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_extreme_value_distribution&quot;&gt;extreme value distribution&lt;/a&gt;. Hence, the probability of a same or larger raw score by random chance is given by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[ P(Z&amp;gt;z) = 1 - exp(-e^{-z\pi/\sqrt{6} - \gamma}) \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; is the Euler-Mascheroni constant (&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\approx 0.5772156649\)&lt;/span&gt;). The expectation values can then be found by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[ E(z) = P(z)N_db  \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(N_db\)&lt;/span&gt; is the number of set comparisons made while searching the database. Keiser et al. could then compare these expectation values to find novel drug-target interactions across a large set of drugs and a large set of protein-ligand sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full presentation can be found below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/33171714&quot; width=&quot;476&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;
src=&quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-keiser_predicting_2009&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Keiser MJ, Setola V, Irwin JJ, Laggner C, Abbas AI, Hufeisen SJ, et al. Predicting new molecular targets for known drugs. Nature. 2009;462: 175–181. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1038/nature08506&quot;&gt;10.1038/nature08506&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-hert_quantifying_2008&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Hert J, Keiser MJ, Irwin JJ, Oprea TI, Shoichet BK. Quantifying the relationships among drug classes. J Chem Inf Model. 2008;48: 755–765. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1021/ci8000259&quot;&gt;10.1021/ci8000259&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/predicting-drug-candidate-promiscuity/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/predicting-drug-candidate-promiscuity/</guid>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>math</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Life, Sans Facebook</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been around three months since, after much back and forth in my head, I decided to permanently delete my Facebook account. In that time, I’ve been asked several times why I left, so I opted to write this short post to spell out my thoughts in a more succinct and thorough manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had originally joined Facebook back in 2008 when it was the newest fad among my friends and I. As I remember, it was cool and a lot of fun. The omnipresent social network played an important part in my high-school social life and helped me keep in contact with my friends once we were unleashed onto the world after graduation. My friends were a decent group on the internet and I mostly enjoyed my interactions with them, so I do not have any horror stories to relate. Facebook helped facilitate my long distance relationships by allowing me to keep up with my friends’ new jobs, how they were doing, what classes they were taking, what day their birthday was, etc. Also, seeing something on Facebook served as a conversation springboard when offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why did I leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe there’s a need to forget, to move on. Both for me and for my friends. People naturally drift apart; Facebook undermines that and ends up creating superficial, passive connections. I also like the mysteriousness of new relationships, the process of discovering things about another person. Facebook ruins that completely by giving you immediate access to their entire social history once you “friend” them. I have no desire to see that, or for others to see mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tailor myself—as almost everyone does—to the people I’m with. I do that, not because I’m disingenuous, but because I have a wide variety of passions and my friends may not share specific interests. Facebook makes the tailoring process more difficult than other social media platforms because people expect you to only have one account. On a similar note, I prefer private correspondence with friends, which contrasts with Facebook’s “share everything with everyone” attitude. That’s a big cup of no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Futhermore, I’m somewhat a minimalist by nature. Facebook is the antithesis of minimalism; more is always more in Facebook land. I disliked having to micromanage my account, which had become almost expected of everyone. I’m also less sentimental and nostalgic than most, so Facebook’s forced persistence of my past did little to benefit me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are idealogical reasons as well. I dislike Facebook’s attitude towards privacy. It’s very difficult to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2012/12/26/oops-mark-zuckerbergs-sister-has-a-private-facebook-photo-go-public/&quot;&gt;control who can see your posts&lt;/a&gt; and deleting isn’t &lt;a href=&quot;http://wellpreparedmind.wordpress.com/2012/10/24/dont-be-fooled-facebook-is-forever/&quot;&gt;actually deleting&lt;/a&gt;. Also, it is very difficult to get a picture of yours—or of you—removed from Facebook. The untagging feature is simply inadequate. I understand that they need to run a business, but I disagree that it is only sustainable through intrusive data-mining and advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Facebook has a dangerous monopoly on our online social lives. People automatically assume that you have one and when you don’t, they’re often stunned. I could not and would not support that because it hurts innovation and it could have &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criticism_of_Facebook#Accusation_of_politically_biased_granting_of_group_upgrades&quot;&gt;unwanted side effects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were just some of the thoughts racing through my head that November night when I yanked the plug on Facebook. It wasn’t an easy decision&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but I feel like it was the right one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or task. Getting pictures, contacts, birthdays, etc. off of Facebook is a major pain.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/life-sans-facebook/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/life-sans-facebook/</guid>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        <category>minimalism</category>
        
        <category>social media</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scholarly Markdown for Scientific Writing </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Scientific writing has come a long way since typewriters and stacks of handwritten reference cards. Robust reference managers, automatically generated bibliographies, and editable files are significant improvements. However, we’re saddled with a myriad of incompatible file formats that are ill-suited for scientific articles. If you’re unlucky then your journal of choice only takes binary blobs with a .docx extension, but otherwise you essentially have two choices: MS Word and LaTeX. Both of which have their respective advantages. The former is better for collaboration, has a lower initial learning curve, and is widely adopted. The latter has superior typography, superior math support, a better file format, and it plays nicely with version control&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, both are dreadful for scientific writing. I could spill a novel-worth of ink on the fallibilities of MS Word, but I’ll be brief. Binary files have a limited shelf-life, science does not. Try to open an article written in Word (or an Excel file full of critical data) from the 90s. It’s probably a garbled mess. Word also suffers from its &lt;a href=&quot;http://fluff.info/terrible/&quot;&gt;lackadaisical support for semantic markup&lt;/a&gt;, its WYSIWYG nature, its &lt;a href=&quot;http://stevenpoole.net/blog/goodbye-cruel-word/&quot;&gt;printed-page focused design&lt;/a&gt;, its inconsistency, its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2013/10/why-microsoft-word-must-die.html&quot;&gt;primitive outlining and tagging features&lt;/a&gt;, its lack of interoperability. The other option, LaTeX, isn’t much better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s saddled with an exceedingly obtuse syntax&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses hundreds of slightly different, inconsistently documented packages&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s impossible to read raw tex (see 1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will completely break from one misplaced character&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It generates somewhere between 5 to 10,000 different files during the compilation process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Much of its documentation is out of date due to its age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lest I forget, debugging LaTeX is impossible. Even its advocates concede that it produces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . . error messages that are mystical, opaque, and vaguely frightening. Experience soon teaches you that the best thing is to ignore the messages . . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- TeX Unbound (Alan Hoenig, p. 447)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the sad state of scientific writing in which we find ourselves. Typesetting is hard, but it shouldn’t be &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, a universal markup converter and extension of the Markdown language, which intends to ameliorate this problem. In direct contrast to LaTeX, &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;’s philosophy is to be “publishable as-is, as plain text, without looking like it’s been marked up with tags or formatting instructions.” The original Markdown language is fairly limited, intending only to produce basic HTML, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/README.html#pandocs-markdown&quot;&gt;Pandoc’s Markdown&lt;/a&gt; goes a step further by allowing tables, footnotes, equations, and internal references that are necessary for scientific writing. Its citation abilities are particularly simple and robust, just add &lt;code&gt;[@Smith2012]&lt;/code&gt; to cite the document with the ID Smith2012 in your BibTex library. It’s nice to have another format to markup our articles, but the nice thing with Pandoc is that you can later convert it to a more “accepted” format. Pandoc’s command line tool has the ability to take your Markdown text and convert it to LaTeX or Word or HTML or any other of the dozens of available formats. It works remarkably well, even with complex LaTeX equations embedded in the document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, should you start using Pandoc for your writing? My answer is yes, but with several caveats. Pandoc is a very young project so it is still missing certain features&lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I’ve run into several bugs. Another issue with Pandoc is loss of fine-grained control over the final output, but this is a mainly a problem for short documents because you can invest the time to write a specific template for longer ones. Nevertheless, it is under &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jgm/pandoc/commits/master&quot;&gt;heavy development&lt;/a&gt; and I expect it to rapidly improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that scholarly markdown, e.g. Pandoc and Multimarkdown, as a whole has a bright future, especially if combined with a solid GUI editor&lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A good GUI would help promote markdown with non-programmers and would help us focus on our writing instead of the specifics of Markdown syntax. Ideally, such an editor would have two views—one for the source and one for the output—but you could write in either one. Such a dual interface would allow for the benefits of GUI’s, e.g. easy table creation, and the precision editing of a plain-text editor. It would be especially nice if scientific journals accepted markdown as a viable submission format, using Pandoc with custom templates behind-the-scenes to generate a beautiful end-result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, if scholarly markdown can be standardized to a suitable degree, combined with a solid GUI editor, and accepted by journals then it could provide a simple, but powerful alternative to Word and LaTeX for scientific writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You’ll find out here shortly that the situation is not as one-sided as I make it seem, despite my opinion that MS Word needs to remain in the enterprise world of disposable documents.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;\textbf{}&lt;/code&gt; for bold? &lt;code&gt;\begin{enumerate} \item \end{enumerate}&lt;/code&gt; for lists? &lt;em&gt;Sigh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this day and age, why do I have to manually import &lt;code&gt;graphicx&lt;/code&gt;? Or use &lt;code&gt;hyperref&lt;/code&gt; so that a single URL doesn’t break everything.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn4&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, I am unaware of a way to reference figures that works in both Word and LaTeX. Apparently, there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9434536/how-do-i-make-a-reference-to-a-figure-in-markdown-using-pandoc&quot;&gt;method&lt;/a&gt; that works if you’re exporting to PDF via LaTeX.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn5&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://texts.io&quot;&gt;Texts.io&lt;/a&gt; is good start.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/scientific-writing-pandoc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/scientific-writing-pandoc/</guid>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
        <category>markdown</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Open Source Software (OSS) approach can be loosely defined as the public release of source code to be freely viewed, modified, and redistributed under a given license. This short essay explores various aspects of the OSS model, touches on some common misconceptions, and considers some of its shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to draw parallels between OSS and scientific research because the scientific method is, intrinsically, an open source process. Science is built on replication and peer-review; therefore, it is requisite that the methodology be made available for scrutiny. Since there are thousands of researchers working on all of its facets, science progresses at a rapid pace with a high level of accuracy and innovativeness. It is the sharing of ideas, work, and results that allows the whole process to function. In the same manner as scientific theories, software will become more robust if more people look at it, tinker with it, and break it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not, however, a basic science. Open Source produces a tangible result—the software—in addition to its intellectual contributions. Thus it is most analogous to the applied biomedical and chemical fields where the goal is to produce an end product. Thus, unsurprisingly, commercial interests (especially IBM, Novell, etc.) are heavily involved in OSS, as they are with the other aforementioned applied fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, OSS is fundamentally unique among the applied sciences in that the actual duplication and implementation cost is trivial. The code can be copied and inserted easily into an ongoing project with minimal effort. Additionally, software is unique in that widespread usage is generally advantageous (e.g. Apache) because that leads to more users uncovering bugs and submitting patches, which then contributes to the further propagation of the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promoting usage is not the only motivation for choosing the open source development model. A project may be open sourced for a variety of reasons, but altruism is generally fairly low on the list. A common misconception is that, because the end product is given away for free, OSS developers will not be compensated for their work. The same could be said of other scientific research because the knowledge is being given without any expectation of direct repayment. This view avoids the importance of resume and reputation building. Showing a potential employer real, useful examples of one’s work is a large bonus; it shows enjoyment of coding and the possession of applicable programming knowledge. Additionally, one may get recommendations from within in the OSS community based on one’s work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned independent developers are predominant on small, specific projects, but paid OSS developers are now the principal contributors to most large OSS projects like Linux. Corporations often have several full-time software engineers working on various OSS projects. Their reasons for doing so can be placed into three distinct categories: (1) the company sells hardware that runs the target OSS project like Intel or IBM, (2) the company sells services that run or use the OSS project like Microsoft’s Azure, or (3) the company provides paid support for the OSS project, e.g. Novell or Red Hat. Richard Stallman may think that the association with industry is an inherent negative, but the current situation is a quantum improvement over the homogeneous closed-development models of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security is often other reason for choosing open source, albeit one that is perhaps slightly counterintuitive and hotly debated. Open-sourced cryptosystems have to, by definition, satisfy &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.tufts.edu/comp/165/classpages/Intro/Kerckhoffs.html&quot;&gt;Kerckhoffs’s principle&lt;/a&gt;, which inherently makes them more robust than closed-sourced ones. That is, open sourced cryptosystems have to designed in such a way that they are secure even if everything about the system, except the private key itself, is publicly available. Pretty Good Privacy (PGP) is one such example; it is considered a military-grade cryptosystem and is completely open-sourced. Additionally, open-sourced cryptosystems build trust, because users know that there are no secret backdoors or glaring vulnerabilities. Cryptography systems designed with OSS in mind are immune to reverse engineering, contrasting with many “Security through obscurity” techniques. However, simply making the source available will not guarantee better security, as the recent Cryptocat &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/security/2013/07/bad-kitty-rooky-mistake-in-cryptocat-chat-app-makes-cracking-a-snap/&quot;&gt;debacle&lt;/a&gt; showed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rookie mistakes, like those committed by the Cryptocat developers, are only a subset of the limitations of open source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source does work, but it is most definitely not a panacea. Software is hard. The issues aren’t that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jwz.org/gruntle/nomo.html&quot;&gt;Jamie Zawinski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It suffers from many of the same difficulties that beset academia: the clashing of strong personalities working on the same project, lack of focus/direction (especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/fork-a-repo&quot;&gt;forking&lt;/a&gt;), focus on power users, among other things. That being said, open source is oft superior to closed-source solutions. It is with good reason that most supercomputers and mission-critical appliances run OSS. It is not a magic bullet and it will not lead to a free software “utopia.” It is software development that mirrors applied scientific research that offers a real solution to many real problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/open/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.tamasnagy.com/blog/open/</guid>
        
        <category>oss</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
